Okay, welcome to the last
session of our six session journey.
The first part tonight is Bob Jones and he's
going to talk to us about something that I
raised at the beginning.
In the first session, I had a list of
questions for you to think about if you're going to
start a venture.
Most of those were factual things like, you
know, do you need a corporation, you know,
how do you find a customer, those sort of things.
But there was one slide that was about
more personal things, you know, is this right for
you?
You know, what does it mean for you?
Well, Bob is going to sort of explore
that in more detail in just a moment here.
So he doesn't need introduction.
You've seen him before.
And take it away, Bob.
Okay.
Bob Jones.
Would you like a…
I'm so wired up tonight that if there's
like a gravitational wave that comes by, I'm
probably going to burst into flames.
So good evening.
I do have a talk for tonight,
but before we get too far into it.
Okay.
There you go.
Thank you.
I'd like to turn that around a little
bit and actually ask you your thoughts about this
course because we've been doing it for a long time.
And I actually, to a considerable extent,
redo every one of my presentations every year,
which is probably a sign that I need medication.
Okay.
And I want to keep what's good.
I want to dump what isn't.
And in spirit of continuous improvement, you guys
had choices for what you could do during
IAP.
And for whatever combination of
reasons, you took this course.
So I'd love to hear a few comments
from you as to what did you expect?
What did you get?
How did they compare?
And did you get any value out of this?
Janet, I'm probably going to put
you to work because handing out microphones.
But how about it?
Give us a little bit of feedback, please.
You can see why Janet wears sneakers for these things.
I'm a second year MBA student and
looking into entrepreneurship for the past two years.
And I think there's something to be
said about distilling all this information into only
six lessons.
And I've actually found a lot of utility in that.
Like you're really looking at the
whole process of how to do it.
And I think that's what I've
been doing for the last two years.
been doing for the last three years.
And I think that's what I've
been doing for the last four years.
been doing for the last five years.
And I think that's what I've
been doing for the last six years.
I can see it's very useful
in just going into the future.
One, I think, point that really just stuck
with me in the course because everything else
has just been at a very
high level is the negotiation piece.
I just personally wish that there was a little
bit more content meet all of those as opposed
to going through an extra class.
Just like seeing like what are the core principles?
And then I just began doing the other stuff.
without negotiating and getting to the initial results.
Awesome.
Thank you.
Kurt, for what it's worth, the
battery in this gizmo has died.
So if you could do
a little surgery, I'd be grateful.
Thank you.
All right, someone else?
So I think a lot
of us came with different experiences
into this course.
What I appreciate is I never got any formal training
in business.
I've been doing it for 25 years.
And it was enlightening and motivating to see this
and to now really understand some of these things
so that I can go dig
into it a little bit more,
as I'm now embarking on my own entrepreneur journey.
So let me dig into that a little bit.
Are you saying that there were actually
practical things?
I mean, were there practical lessons that you got out
of this or that we
covered topics that you had never
covered before?
Flesh that out a little bit, please.
I saw some of the reasons why
I was doing some of the things.
So some of the things that
I had applied and going through,
for example, financial projections and all that,
I had to learn all the job.
I never did it before.
Yup.
OK.
I just want to say that
also, is a lot of it
about the learning perspective, this type of perspective.
I have to second with regards to negotiations,
just because I've been part of a lot of negotiations,
that it would have been nice
to have a little bit more
of the theory.
Brilliant.
Thank you.
Rather than jumping in.
It was a good exercise, nonetheless.
Well, the point you made
that people come into this course
with vastly different backgrounds, of course,
makes it challenging for the presenters.
these things where some of
the participants were freshmen, some were
faculty members, several had already had two
startups, and a couple who came in
and said I took the course two years ago,
I had a startup, it flopped, I'm back to
see what it was I should have
paid attention to and didn't. All right, anyone
else want to add something
to that? Yes sir? Congratulations.
I think you just volunteered to teach
a session next year because I think
that's actually kind of the heart of the
matter which is that we we spend a
lot of time articulating high-level
principles in our schooling, and we
sometimes trip when we when those
principles collide with the reality, and
sometimes that I find it very helpful to
say, well if I know what your customers
want and give it to them,
it's like well duh, but it gets
tough.
overlooked frequently. So thank
you, that's helpful. Anyone else?
And we've got one gentleman here
and then we'll close this out.
So thank you for the sessions.
I don't have any entrepreneurial experience so
each of the sessions was of immense value for
me. One thing that I can think of could
further help, especially with the numbers or
the pitch is getting access to existing startups
pitches or some numbers that they generated. If we
have experience, if we have access to that, I think
it would help us in connecting the parts that okay,
if I'm trying to forecast sales, how would it be
as it could look like?
I think there is a link for some pitches
that I think would be helpful, but other than that,
similar resources. That would be very helpful. Thank
you. That is a topic that every now and
then Joe and I have knocked around a little
bit, which is we've got a substantial list of people
who have gone through the process of creating a
platform, and they've been able to get a lot of
information about the process of creating a platform.
And so I think that's a great way to
get that information out there. And I think that's
a great way to get that information out there.
through this course over the years. And we
never really have made any effort to try and
create a community out of that. And yet
I think there's real value in that. And well,
I'm going to elaborate on that in my
talk. Entrepreneurs are weird. And they usually don't
have very many friends. And a community of people who
are weird like you can be not only useful, but
quite comforting. So we're going to flag that.
We'll have a follow-on conversation. And you have
the mic, sir. So sorry, you're on. Very cool.
Yeah, so as someone who did university as an
undergrad for two years and decided to drop out
because there's too much of an emphasis on theory
and I'm a very big hands-on person, having to
do it from scratch, you know, I've had, like,
you know, no, like, formal training in my business
or anything like that. This is my first, like,
foray into it at all. And I think that's a
really good way to get that information out there. And
I really, really appreciate it. I guess it would
boil it down for someone who's never looked into
business at all. And there was never a moment
that they were like, there was like a financial
trust and all that where I was like, what
are they talking about? Like, I think it's very straightforward.
And I really appreciate that. Good. All right.
That's very helpful. If you think of a major
topic that we should have included but didn't,
and we should build it in for next year,
tell Janet. And have her, do you have a
final remark you want to make? All right, Janet,
we're going to have one more here. And then I want
to get to the subject matter at hand. Go ahead, ma'am.
I have a statement from the National Digital Advisory for Public
Companies and I found it very practical that we use marketing
way, especially with the fashion metric and the fashion.
Financing sources.
Yeah.
Hold on a second. Remember what I said about microphones?
Yes.
Okay. Find out what your customer wants, give
it to them. Great. All right. Thank you very
much.
Thank you.
The feedback is valuable, and I don't know how often
you've had people running courses ask you what you thought
and whether or not it could be made better, but
we're pretty serious about that whole sort of customer discovery thing.
So tonight's agenda, stories.
And then we're going to talk about some of
the hard stuff about entrepreneurship that rarely gets talked about.
Some lessons, and we'll wrap it up.
This is kind of obligatory because these are freestanding, and you
guys have seen it by now, so I'll just blast through it.
I started some companies. I wrote a book. I
had a turnaround job. I had a couple normal jobs.
Went to a couple schools. I'm a working musician.
I'm playing next Saturday in the morning as
a soloist, solo guitarist at the Pine Street.
Women's shelter for their Valentine's Day tea.
And then that evening, in a complete reversal,
I'm playing the blues at a brewery in Marlborough.
And of note, you guys should pay attention to
MIT's Venture Mentoring Service if you ever pursue this,
and anyone in your senior management
team has any affiliation with MIT.
Okay.
How many of you guys have already?
Have you been through something like Y Combinator
or Techstars or some sort of incubator for training?
Okay.
Well, we'll get some comments from you
as to how this compares at some point.
Some of the popular myths about
startups, there's a lot of money available.
And if I bring my amazing idea to
investors, they will just shower me with money.
So, might there be some
part of that that's not true?
Maybe.
And there's also some popular
myths about boot camps, for example,
that there is a magic formula for success.
And if you follow the path that we
teach you, you can pretty well be guaranteed
that you will be showered with money.
And there are outfits out there
that kind of halfway promise that.
Okay.
So, I'm going to go ahead and get started.
This left us with a moral dilemma.
Do we hype it, promote the
myths, or do we tell you facts?
We voted for facts because that famous professor,
Hadzima, articulated an equation for you guys.
In your very first session,
happiness is reality divided by expectations.
Tonight, we're going to talk
a little bit about expectations.
Because the facts are, it's hard.
And most startups fail.
And most investors believe that you will probably fail.
You may be brilliant.
You may be charming and lovable, kind to animals.
Investors think you're going to fail.
There are lots of entrepreneurs.
There's lots of competition for
talent, funding, and other resources.
And many of the entrepreneurs won't get the money.
So, why am I talking about this?
Well, when you decided to come
here, or Harvard, or Tufts, or Northeastern,
or Northwestern, or wherever you went,
you probably knew walking in the door
that you were going to take
a beating somewhere along the way.
And so, you probably didn't realize how much
of a beating you were going to take.
But you knew it was going to be hard.
But there are a lot of people who promote entrepreneurship.
And to my, in my opinion, they over glamorize it.
And they don't tell you how hard it is.
So, in the spirit of disclosure, tonight I
want to talk a little bit about the fact
that even the smartest ones fail.
And I know a lot of entrepreneurs.
I don't know a single one
who got everything right the first time.
It's going to be important that you know,
to this community question that you brought up,
you're not alone.
And there are some resources you can draw on.
And I'm going to talk a little
bit about all of that this evening.
I do think that this is very important.
Entrepreneurs solve problems.
They improve lives.
Your new businesses drive growth, create
jobs, and in some cases, create wealth.
And that's a noble endeavor.
But it's hard.
When I was interviewing some of my friends
who are entrepreneurs for the book I wrote,
one of the people who,
who's in the book, failed nine times in a
row before she eventually hit it with number 10.
So, that raises a couple of questions, of course.
How on earth do you
come back after nine consecutive failures?
And also, what did you do differently in
number 10 that caused this one to succeed?
Which sort of became the
paradigm for what I wrote about.
So, tonight is less my session.
Tonight is less about the practicum
that you all said you liked.
So, I may be making
a mistake to deviate from that.
But I want to talk a little bit
about things you may need in the future.
But first, a story that might
cause you to think I accidentally walked
into the wrong room, diving boards.
Until a couple of years ago,
I was a pretty serious springboard diver.
Worked out with a coach
and a small group of lunatics.
At Boston University.
And I was the guy up on the high board doing
stuff that nobody at my advanced stage ought to be doing.
And one summer, I was screwing
around at the outdoor pool in Lexington.
My, at the time, 14-year-old daughter came up and said,
Dad, you know that thing you're
doing with a coach at BU?
Will they take kids?
I said, I can probably make that happen.
Do you want to learn how to do this stuff?
Yeah, I want to learn
how to do that flippy stuff.
And I said, it's hard.
It's terrifying.
You sure you want to do it?
Yep. So, I said, all right.
And I signed her up.
Because I knew that most 14-year-old
girls didn't even want to be
in the same building with their father.
And I wasn't going to pass this up.
So, I knew that there comes
a point for most new divers,
you've learned how to work
the board, you've gotten some altitude,
you've learned a little bit of
basic gymnastics moves, and then you flop.
And I knew that she was
going to get to that point.
And sure enough, the coach realized
she actually had some athletic ability,
sent her up on the high board.
I said, walk to the end of the
board, turn around backwards so the water's behind you.
All right.
And I want you to pull your knees
up close to your chest, both of them,
and balance on the balls of your feet.
Water's behind you.
And then I want you to fall over backwards.
And when I say, hut, I want
you to come out of the tuck,
look back for the water, and go in head first.
Now, the second time you do that,
you think, well, what was the big deal?
That wasn't that.
That wasn't that hard.
The first time you do it, you
think, oh, my God, I'm going to die.
And the last thing I will see is
the ceiling of this pool just before I die.
And sure enough, she rolled over backwards.
And when the coach said, hut,
instead of looking back for the water,
she panicked and did a complete
back flop from the high board.
And all five of us, the
rest of us in the class,
knew exactly what that felt like.
She might have sunk three
or four inches in the water.
She just, tears, bright red back,
came to the edge of the pool,
and we all sort of comforted her for a minute.
And then what about our workouts?
Because I had explained to her in advance.
I said, look, I'm not going to be
one of those tiger dads or helicopter parents
or whatever.
You're going to do this
because you want to do it.
And PS, I need the coaching as well.
So for that time that
we were on the boards together,
we're just fellow divers, OK?
She said, deal.
So I knew she was at a crossroads.
She was either going to decide, this is ridiculous.
I've made a terrible mistake.
That really hurt.
I'm never doing this again.
Or she'd change her mind.
So I continued diving.
After a couple of minutes, I saw her sitting there
looking up at the platform where the two high boards were.
And she got up and she walked over
to the stairs up to the high board.
I said, what are you doing?
She said, I'm going to do it again.
I'm going to get it right.
Yes.
Her decision, right?
And actually, we continued diving for a couple of years.
So she got to high school and discovered boys.
Well, entrepreneurship is a little bit like that
in that you're trying something you've not done before.
And it's scary.
And when you flop, it hurts, particularly
if you've led a life of high achievement.
It's painful.
It's not something you're accustomed to.
And you come to that crossroads.
Now what?
And a fair number of people
say, well, this was a terrible mistake.
I'm never doing it again.
And that's the majority.
And for them, it's the right decision.
A few of you who have wiring defects.
I'm not going to go into that.
I'm going to go into that.
Say, you know, that didn't kill me.
I'm going to do it again.
So think about it.
If you're an innovator, what comes with innovation?
Well, you're doing something new.
You may not have done it before.
Maybe nobody's done it before.
There's no established roadmap,
which raises the alarming possibility
that you might not know what you're doing.
Totally forgivable.
Totally understandable.
But you're not doing it.
You're not doing it.
Many people find uncertainty to be stressful.
And you have to make decisions, a lot of decisions.
And some of those decisions are going to be wrong
because you're moving fast,
you don't have enough information,
and you got to make a decision.
Do we raise the price?
Do we sign a contract with the supplier?
Do I hire this guy?
Do I fire this one?
So you have to ask yourself, can you accept that?
And you have to ask yourself, can you accept that?
Many people find that one of
the appeals of being an entrepreneur is
that you're your own boss.
Is that true for any of you?
Thinking about it?
Yeah? Okay.
Well, here's the good news.
Nobody's going to tell you what to do.
Here's the bad news.
Right? You'll be in a situation you
think, I don't know what to do.
So let me tell you a couple
of stories that my friends that I interviewed
for my book told me.
These are their words, not mine.
Here's Trevor.
Trevor said, well, I became
an entrepreneur when I was 26.
I was on the front page of the newspaper.
I had a brand new hot car.
I had a smoking hot girlfriend.
And I had the world by the horns.
One year later, I'd lost everything.
My car was repossessed, meaning
somebody showed up and took it.
My girlfriend dumped me, and I
was living in my parents' basement,
working as an assistant manager at Radio Shack.
So, well, Trevor, how'd you feel about that?
Took me a couple of years to get
the taste of failure out of my mouth.
And I still remember it vividly every day.
I should point out, by the way,
that Trevor is quite successful these days.
But I decided, I hope you'll see the
analogy to the crossroads decision my daughter made.
Failure is not a fatal experience.
It's a learning experience.
You have to take care of yourself first,
and you have to become a perpetual learner.
And the most important truth is, you have to learn.
And the most important trait for an
entrepreneur to be successful is not intelligence.
Please don't burst into tears.
And it's not creativity.
It's adaptability.
Here's Laura.
Laura is brassy, kind of profane, polarizing
in that there are people who love her
and people who don't want to
be in the same room with her.
أمنا
first category. I think she's awesome. But she
was managing two big businesses for a big company
and had a big paycheck. She quit, walked
away, went all in, joined an entrepreneurial outfit
that Joe and I have done a bit of work
with. And she knew when she walked in, she just concluded,
I'm the smartest person in the room. At 1030
in the morning on the first day, she retreated to
the ladies room in tears, called her husband.
I'd asked her some questions that she found
distressing. Called her husband, I've made a terrible
mistake. I can't do this. I'm not cut
out for this. I have to get my job back.
You have to come get me. Fortunately, her husband had been
married to her for 19 years. He said, Laura, knock
it off. This guy just saved you two years and a
couple hundred thousand bucks by showing you that
you were going to be a good husband.
You're going down the wrong road. Go have another
idea. Okay. Back in she went. She did have another
idea. And it wasn't very good either. She spent a
half a million bucks of her own money. And it was
a bust. More tears, more heartache. So she had
another idea. And in this situation, she ended up
having a coffee one day with a guy that ran
a huge real estate firm. He loved her idea. And
big success.
Pulled together a little side hustle, which
blossomed. Signed a big contract with Hallmark,
the people who make greeting cards. All
of a sudden, everybody says, Laura, you're awesome.
She's always awesome. It just took her a while to
get to the answer. And she said, you know, Bob,
when my second business was tanking, I
remembered your story about the kidney failure product.
You guys may remember that from our first night together.
And I figured out my prospects
are never going to use my product.
Lesson, validate, validate, validate. Talk to your customers.
If they don't want it, you can't sell it.
And the lessons from talking to the real estate
guy, she just buttonholed him one day. Their kids
were on the same swim team. And she didn't
even realize what a hot ticket he was. She said,
would you have coffee with me and
help me understand something? I've got this little
business going and it's taking off and I don't know
what to do. And I said, well, I'm going to
buy it. I don't know why. And he looked at it and he
said, I can tell you why I want it for all of my
agents. And she said, okay. He said, no, I want
it for all my agents. There are 11,000 of them.
Whoa, who is this guy? Anyway, value of reaching out.
And she had something where they won if she won.
Okay. Reaction so far? Any takeaways?
I think I should know from you. Some years
ago, I figured out when I was interviewing people,
if I found somebody I really liked and wanted to
hire them, I would spend a fair amount of time
explaining to them all the reasons why they should
not take the job. It's going to be really hard.
It's going to be really risky. We're probably
going to fail. See that curb outside? You're
likely to be sitting out on that curb
unemployed before long. And if they started grinning,
I knew I had the right person. Right?
You're grinning. You may be ready for
this. Here's a few of my thoughts.
This is a lonely life. And it's hard to find
anybody to talk to. And what I'm about to tell
you is a parable, but it's based on a lot
of stories from a lot of entrepreneurs that I have
distilled. And forgive me, I'm going to
use old school 50s type dynamics here.
Jack and Jill.
Jill were both gainfully
employed, accomplished professionals. One day,
they decided to start a family. They concluded that
one of them should stay home and take care
of the kids. Jack lost the coin toss and he
stayed at work. Jill stayed home. Jack, after a while,
quit his job at Amazon and joined
a startup. In fact, started a business.
After an offer, he ran away, leaving Chanel
consults to a bank and got her Güang's
P sleeves.
producto?
Aquí está.
變oupe sale cows bambam Touch.
Pollack slices,
only one vending machine.
Zip it guys,
you can get a wonderful僰
by casket seventh.
doing? And Jill at the moment had
just changed two dirty diapers and mopped up
strained carrots from the floor and she
said, she exploded. She said, what do you
mean you don't know what you're doing?
Do you realize we've got a mortgage, we've
got two kids, we need to be saving
money and you took this crazy job and you're
telling me you don't know what you're
doing? Have you lost your mind? Which
caused two thoughts for Jack. One was, oh
dear, she's right. And the other was, that
didn't work very well, I don't think I'm
gonna do that anymore. Right? I think if I
have self-doubt I'll just leave it at work.
But the fact is if you're gonna go
do this you're gonna be
rejected constantly. Potential clients will tell
you no, partners will tell you no,
people that you want money from they'll tell
you no, potential employees they'll say no
I'm gonna take a job somewhere else.
And it's hard to find a shoulder to cry
on. And if you have lived a life where
you have been accomplished and you've
been rewarded for being smart and for
your awesome work ethic, this, this
will be difficult. And it is unfortunately
true that not everyone has your
best interests at heart. My friend Glennppen
海克
Group of Platforms
built a good business. Over six years, he
worked very hard. One summer, his wife's father said,
you know, I've come into some money, and
I'm going to take the whole family to Europe,
and I'm paying all the expenses, two weeks vacation.
He said, I can't go. I have to stay
home and work. He raised capital. He
secured customers. His business was growing nicely.
And then his investors stole the company from
him. He found that to be difficult. So, sidebar,
two lessons. Don't raise money from the
wrong people. And protect your intellectual property.
In other words, if you've got
a magic algorithm or secret business formula,
protect it. So, the risk of pushing
a few more of you off the cliff.
Meet your constant companions. Anxiety,
self-doubt, imposter syndrome. Let's unpack
that a little bit. If you're running a company, there
are a lot of people that are counting on you.
Your family, your employees, maybe even
your customers. And when you flop,
you go home one day, and you're going to be in a
lot of trouble. And you're going to be in a lot of trouble.
So, if you've got a magic algorithm, you're
holding on to it for courses and years.
Thank you.
And the guidance from faith, sickness,oure they will trap.
It also tells us that we scorn people.
And even Jellyfish, thank you, friend failure-
Many que ensuite desparate feelings.
You met your destiny yourself.
And at the end of the day, you're in a
life of need, but then you're used to community and
evaluation against you are the problem.
However, guys, it enjoyed the culture.
person for the job. You have been presenting
yourself as the capable captain of the ship,
but secretly you worry maybe you're not.
Maybe you're a fraud. Maybe you're a poser.
These are disturbing thoughts. So is there hope for us?
Well, accept up front that normal people
can't help you because you're not normal.
Right? I mean, serial
entrepreneurs are just wired differently.
If you were normal, you'd work for Amazon.
Your normal friends don't understand why you're not
working for Amazon. You have made life choices that
they think are crazy. And if you come to
them wanting to boohoo a little bit
because things aren't going well, they think, well,
of course they're not going well. You're a dumbass
for even doing this. You should be doing this other
thing. We have nice things going on. You're a
dumbass for even doing this. You should be doing
this other thing. You're a dumbass for even
doing this. You should be doing this other thing.
You're a dumbass for even doing this. You should be
doing this other thing. You've got to be able to
have a stable income. So they can't counsel you.
So the answer? Find a community of people who are
as crazy as you are, which you sort of brought
up and which we probably need to do more with.
But Joe and I, as mentioned, spent a decade
or more working with a group that works with high
growth entrepreneurs in the Midwest.
And over and over again,
they would meet in Kansas City or Wichita
or whatever and come into the room and say,
I thought I was the only crazy person out there.
I'm in a room full of people like me. These are
my peeps. And in short order, like half hour,
they'd all be sitting at the bar swapping all
kinds of details about their life stories because
they were kindred spirits. So find a group like
that. We may be able to help. Seek their
counsel. Help them as well. Because there will be times
when that support network is a lifeline. Shifting
gears for a second, I think this is really
important. There's this word, pivot, that gets batted
around as a synonym for, I didn't know
what I was doing.
and so I changed.
And that's actually OK, because scientists
articulate a hypothesis and test it.
And if the hypothesis proves to be wrong,
they say, well, time for the next hypothesis.
If your business fails, in a
lot of places in the US,
the feeling in the community is if your business failed,
then you're a failure.
Fortunately, in places like Boston and a few places
in the West Coast, you'll talk to people,
and you'll, after a while, say, yeah, my business flopped.
And they say, ah, dude, mine failed three times.
Welcome.
Keep going, because you are testing hypotheses.
This is a re-engineering of your mindset here.
You are testing hypotheses, and what you did
was found wrong.
You found one that didn't work.
Time for a new hypothesis.
To use a different analogy,
you may be a talented jockey.
You may have just picked the wrong horse.
Shoot it.
Find a new horse.
One thing you can do, and I
have found this to be a lifesaver,
is get a business advisory board.
These are experts.
They're experts who are not just experts.
They're experts who want you to succeed.
They're helping you for mainly, well, partly because they
like you, you hope, and mostly because they
want to see you succeed.
This is not the same as a board of directors.
A board of directors, as you no doubt
have learned in the course of
the past week and a half,
they represent the shareholders.
And they are not only
empowered to fire you, but obligated
to fire you.
That's not usually a good
place to stand up and say,
I haven't the slightest idea of what I'm doing.
Business advisory board does not have
those fiduciary responsibilities.
It's a great place to stand up and say,
I have no clue what to do next.
Just a quick story.
At one point, I, along with
one of my genius scientist friends,
had invented a 2 and 1 half ounce drink.
They were a little bit expensive.
They needed to be a little bit more expensive.
They were a little bit cheaper.
They didn't use the same drink.
They were just a little bit more expensive.
And I said, well, how
do you find the right drink?
Well, the question is, is it not the same drink
that you drink every day?
Is it the same drink that you drink every day?
Is it the same drink that you drink every night?
And he said, no, it's not the same drink.
It's the same drink that you drink every day.
Well, I don't know if I have the slightest idea
how to find a manufacturer who
can bottle a beverage like this,
in quantities less than 2
million bottles, which I can't afford.
Two days later, problem solved.
So it really helps if you just assemble some
people who think, you might have a big idea
and I know something about this.
I might be able in this narrow arena help you.
Interestingly, about a year into it I realized
these people have helped me over and over
again and I've never done a thing for them.
I feel guilty.
I can't give them any
money, I don't have any money.
I should give them equity.
Some ownership in the company.
And I didn't know how much to give them.
So I asked them.
I said I'm thinking of giving you guys some equity.
I feel obligated to do that and I'm grateful
for your help and my business would have died
six months ago without your help.
And I don't know how much to give you.
You're my advisors, advise me.
I trusted them obviously.
I said I was thinking of giving
you one point a piece, one percent.
And they said, no.
That's too much.
Give us a half a point a piece.
That's more appropriate.
And when you show your capitalization
table to prospective investors, they will acknowledge
that you made a sophisticated decision
and it will help you raise capital.
I thought, I love these guys.
Attitudes that will help, what I found to
be the right blend is if they listen more
than they talk.
If their attitude is I want to show you that
I'm the smartest guy in the room and I know
everything, that's not going to be productive.
Most of them you want to be cheerleaders so
that you can stand in front of them and say
I fell down and they
say don't worry, you'll get up.
But it really helps if you have one or
two who will give you ten reasons why your idea
or the steps you're going to take won't work.
I had one of those guys.
He was pretty sophisticated.
Worked at Nestle.
Had seen all manner of
ideas, most of which didn't work.
And he had a long list of
sensible, validated reasons why things wouldn't work.
And he'd throw out ten of these things.
And I think I got you here, here, here.
I had seven of them covered.
Three of them I would think,
oh, God, I didn't think of that.
So I find that to be a useful balance.
Are you guys okay with this question?
Yes, sir.
Not to dive too much into the details
of the advisory board, but how would you recommend
we structure or add some sort of
framework or structure behind their role responsibilities?
Does that look like an option?
Is there an issue that says, hey, we
want someone to sit down, talk about business challenges,
growth, solutions, all those sorts of things?
Yeah.
I think that's a good question.
Thank you for the question.
I don't have what is considered best practices.
I don't know.
What I did with every time I did one
of these, because I knew these people and I trusted
them, I would simply have a
call with them and we'd chat.
And I would say, look, I don't want
to burden you with a lot of stuff.
What I want is to have a conversation.
I don't want to burden
you with a lot of stuff.
I want to be able to call you every now
and then and something that is your area of expertise
and not mine.
And we'll probably have a meeting
for two hours every other month.
And my goal is we take what you know and
what the other advisors know and add it to the
little bit that I know
and we'll build a great company.
And they all said, okay.
I've been loving what you're doing.
This idea is cool.
I'm in.
It was that straightforward.
And the only time we put together a document
was when I finally figured out I ought to
give them some equity and we had to put
together something that said here are the options and
the vesting processes and you should file
an 83 election and blah, blah, blah.
But prior to that, it was all a handshake.
Anybody else?
Questions?
We have a question right behind you, Jim.
Yes, sir.
From a personal standpoint, would you say
that the threshold for having a chance to
succeed from a startup going from zero to one
is that you have to view the idea as something
that you have to attempt?
Are you asking me if the success
criterion is I get so fired up?
I think I just have to do this?
Yeah, it's not like the
threshold of getting into that chance.
I think that is a double-edged sword in
that it's the right level of passion will cause
you to think I might work on Saturday
and every now and then and get something done
and I'm going to get back
up after I've been knocked down.
Too much passion blinds you to the obvious.
And I think if you meter into that, yeah, but
I also got to make a living and I got
to deal with my family and support them.
And on a good day, I actually like my children.
I wouldn't mind spending some time
with them and having some balance.
So I think Tuesday night when we
talked about pitching, I said deploy passion wisely.
Okay.
Because if your pitch is so passionate that
they fear you're just going to have a seizure
or something, then you're unlikely to attract investment.
And I think similarly when you're looking
to start something, if it really gets you
fired up and you think, God, I would
love to do this, that's a really good sign.
If you think, well, I'm just not going to
eat or sleep or shower or see anybody, that's
not a good sign.
Reasonable answer?
Yes, thank you.
You're welcome.
Okay.
Oh, backed up.
I'm sorry.
There is something that I left off here.
There are resources around.
Harvard's got the iLab.
MIT's got Venture Mentoring Service.
Most of the schools have discovered that
there is an appetite for entrepreneurship amongst
their constituency and they have responded.
So find those resources and avail yourself of them.
Okay.
Thank you.
And this is sort of an elaboration on the
question that you just asked me, but an awful
lot of entrepreneurs also think that they
really can't do anything else 24-7 but work
on their business.
And I think that's a really bad
idea because you have to make good decisions.
And it doesn't matter how smart you
are, how strong your work ethic is.
There are 168 hours in the
week no matter who you are.
And if you spend every one of them on
your work ethic, you're going to get to work.
That's the best way to do it.
And I think that's a really good idea.
Dr. P. Smith?
working on your business, there will come
a point when you will self-destruct. So
not to sound like your grandmother, but
there are some obvious steps which are
frequently ignored. Enough with the carryout
pizzas. Eat a decent meal now
and then. Get some exercise. It's
incredible for helping you manage stress.
There's a lot of literature out
there that says a five-minute walk has
extraordinary benefits in reducing your stress
levels. And because I was in the
sleep business for a while, I ran across
a bunch of statistics to the effect that
sleeping only five hours a night
causes the same impairment to your cognitive
abilities as three drinks.
So you're operating probably beyond the
legal level for intoxication most of the
time. Ask yourself, are you making the
best decisions for you and your company?
Get some sleep. Go home. Take care of
your loved ones because they're going to be
important to you long after
your business has failed or succeeded.
There was one year when I missed Halloween
with my kids who wanted to walk around in
costumes and have me take them with them.
And they remembered that I missed their Halloween
long after I remembered why I missed
their Halloween. And when that happened, I said,
OK, new rules. I'm not doing that anymore.
Right? Business issues will be there in the
morning.
recharge your batteries. This is hard. It drains
you. Do stuff you love. Some of you
run, some of you climb rocks, some
of you are artistically gifted, some of us
blunder our way into playing music.
Whatever it is, do stuff that recharges
your battery. Your business will be better off
and so will you. I had a party
when I launched my book. Picked up a
lovely place on the seaport. I had a
whole bunch of lunatic entrepreneur
friends from Kansas and Nebraska and
Oklahoma who flew in on their own dime
to come and a bunch of people here in
Boston to come. It was kind
of exciting. Writing a book was extraordinarily
harder than I expected it to be. After a
lot of false starts, I had ended up with
something I was kind of proud of.
I was kind of proud of my book. I was
kind of proud of my book. I was kind of
proud of it. I thought it was kind
of cool to have a launch party. I didn't
want it just to be cocktails and hors
d'oeuvres. I wanted to have a little bit
of a panel discussion talking a
little bit about entrepreneurship. So I
snagged three of the entrepreneurs and I
had them sit at little stools up front.
Each of them had a microphone and I
asked them a question. I said, you're in a
room full of people who either
are entrepreneurs or are thinking of being
entrepreneurs. What's the most important piece
of advice you could give them? Just
like that, with no coordination whatsoever, all
three of them said, don't do it. Whoa!
This sort of underscores the lawyer's maxim,
don't ask a question you don't know the
answer to. I thought, oops.
But it did raise two questions.
Why on earth would you say that? And
given that all three of you are running
startups now, and some of you for
the second or third time, why are you
ignoring your own advice? So
a provocative discussion followed. And to
that extent a question you may be
asking yourself right now is, why on earth
would anybody do this? If
it's as difficult and maybe even
dreary as I'm describing it, why would
you do it? Well, some of their answers,
you have to. This piggybacks on your question,
right? You feel a real drive to create something
that's better. You want to be your own boss, even to
the point where you'll take a pay cut to do it.
Maybe you're just too weird to do
anything else, right? You found that that corporate
culture was a lot like that pair of shoes
that looked great on the shelf, but when you walked
around in them for a while, you find yourself
thinking, I can't wait to get out of these things.
They just don't fit me. Maybe you want to improve
your business by doing something that's better. Maybe
you want to improve your business by doing
something that's better. Maybe you want to
improve the quality of life for others.
I had an entrepreneur, had a
pretty successful business go in St. Louis,
healthcare software, pretty cool. And he called me up
one day and said, Bob, you told me to find
my customers. I found more than I expected. I
don't know how to select where I ought to go.
Can I spend a day with you? I sat on a
whiteboard and smoked my way through this and helped me make
some choices. I said, yeah. Come on
into town the night before. I'll take you.
I'll take you to a sleazy seafood restaurant
and we might have an adult beverage or two,
and then we'll work all day the
next day. And we did and he did.
I was operating under the assumption that what
he wanted to do was grow this company
to the point where somebody came along and bought
it, enjoy his wealth for a year or two,
go do another one. And he would say, yes,
yes, that's right. But when we talked about that,
he was engaged but not animated. And you
know, when you're having dinner with somebody and maybe
enjoying a beverage or two, conversations tend to
drift a little bit. And he started talking
about this orphanage in Venezuela that he was
sending money to and sending resources to and
was supporting. And when he described that, he
would light up like the Christmas tree in Times
Square. And he would say, I'm going to go
to the Christmas tree in Times Square. And I said,
I'm going to go to the Christmas tree in Times
Square. And he would say, I'm going to go to the
Christmas tree in Times Square. And he would say, I'm
going to go to the Christmas tree in Times Square.
And he would say, I'm going to go to the
Christmas tree in Times Square. And about midway through the
next morning, as we were working through all of
these sort of triage exercises, I said, you know,
I don't think you're looking at this the way you
should be looking at it. I don't think you want to
go hell bent on growing a company that investors
will love and someone will come along and acquire
it. I think what you want to do is
legitimately build a great company. And if somebody comes along
someday and says, I'd like to buy it, you'll have
the conversation. But what you want to do is build
a great company that allows you to spend
some time on these philanthropic efforts that you really
like. And he stood there for 30 or 40 seconds.
And then he went, I feel so much better. He says,
you're absolutely right. I've been going down
the wrong road all this time. So,
I'm going to go to the Christmas tree in Times
Square. And he would say, I'm going to go to the
Christmas tree in Times Square. And he would say, I'm going to
go to the Christmas tree in Times Square. And he would say,
you know, maybe you want to improve
the quality of life for other people.
One more story like this. Another of
the entrepreneurs was involved in the business
of bringing internet access to sections of rural
Nebraska. I thought, well, that doesn't sound very
glamorous. Why are you doing it? And he said,
I'll give you an example of why I'm doing it.
There's a woman out there, call her Carol.
Carol doesn't have internet access. All her kids
get their homework assigned online, and what she
has been doing for the last couple of years
is leaving work at two o'clock, picks her kids
up from school, and parks the car outside the library.
So, the kids can piggyback on the Wi-Fi
from the library. They can get their homework assignments,
they can do their homework, and then she
takes them home, points them toward the prepared meal
that she's letting her girls do that one time, and
they can go home. No one wants this broom and broom,
that she's left for him and goes back to work.
And when the day came that we put internet access
in her place, he said, yeah,
I'm the CEO of the company,
but I was doing the install
along with the rest of my guys.
I'm just wearing a shirt that says Mike.
And she came up to me and she says,
you're running this outfit, aren't you?
And he said, well, yes,
ma'am, but that doesn't really matter.
She said, let me show you something.
She said, come in here.
She says, you see that bag of groceries
on the table in the kitchen?
Tonight will be the first night in four years
that I have been able to cook dinner and have
dinner with my children.
And tomorrow, I will be able
to work normal hours and come home
because my kids finally have internet access.
He said, that's why I'm doing it.
Great story or what, right?
So you want to correct something?
It needs to be fixed, which was one
of the things you mentioned in our very first session.
There's a few more answers, all of them legitimate.
Maybe you like the idea
of creating wealth for your family
and for yourself.
Build it, sell it, build some wealth,
spend a year in the Alps or sailing your yacht,
and then do it again.
Maybe you love the buzz.
You get really worked up over cool technology.
Maybe you love the idea of building a business
and building a business that you can
build on the
You need to know the scale.
You need to know the modes.
You need to understand the framework.
You need to know the difference
between three-four time and four-four time.
And I don't know.
I don't know.
But then you have to have something creative going on.
And being a good entrepreneur is a bit like that.
You need lots of creativity,
but you need lots of discipline.
So your reaction so far?
Your thoughts?
Any of this sinking in?
You have questions or comments you'd care to offer?
Janet?
There's one thing you said that struck me
as firmly as the whole six
sessions or five and a half
seminars, and that was the Take care of yourself.
I've been riding motorcycles since before,
close to the other people room of 하고 more,
and, after riding for 25
years, I took motorcycle safety course.
I was teaching at the
Labs School of Bentley and teachingsteaching
insurance and financial planning in West thinks
you cannot get out of school and
you're going to go into become a 60
highs, as complicated and dangerous прош and make
more than you need to be, watch out.
Because if you fail, try to get used to it.
I could have plugged him out of there and
stuck him in front of my class because he
said the first thing you have to understand
is what can kill you when you're riding a
motorcycle.
And he used the exact same example that
you did about sleep and mentioned a few other
things.
So at the core of anything we do is
who's doing it, why are we doing it, the stories
you've been telling me the last 20
minutes and a half hour are just exceptional.
In my past businesses, as I said, I talk
about people's money and I ask them what they want
to do with their money.
I say, well, I want
to earn X, Y, Z money.
I need to do this.
I say, for what?
What do you want to do with it?
I don't care that you want to earn money.
What do you want to do with your money?
And until they can articulate that,
it makes no sense to me.
It's just a question.
Woo!
All right.
We may have to have a longer conversation.
I'm currently on my 12th motorcycle and
took that Motorcycle Safety Foundation course for
advanced riders out on the tarmac at Hanscom Field.
I've got a bit over 100,000 miles of motorcycling
under me, probably 30,000 of them in the rain.
Yeah.
I've gotten sideways on black ice
in Chicago, et cetera, et cetera.
So it is important to identify that it's just not
smart to do that if you are in an impaired
state.
Well, sleepy or maybe these guys that get
off work, put their helmet on, go three blocks
to the bar, drink five beers,
and then get on their motorcycle.
They're called organ donors.
Right?
So entrepreneurship is usually not quite as important.
Entrepreneurship is usually not quite
that dramatic, but frizzed-out entrepreneurs make
bad decisions.
And you might not die, but your business probably will.
Thank you.
Okay.
I'm going to give you the results of
a year of research in probably two bullet points.
Okay?
So you've heard this statistic a few
times, and they vary according to definitions of
what is success.
In the food industry, they ask the question,
is your product still on the shelf two years
later?
And other industries use different metrics, but
you almost can't get away from the fact
that eight or nine out of 10 startups fail.
And I'm going to horribly
oversimplify a lot of complex stuff.
But I think it kind of boils down
to you're missing skills you didn't know you needed.
If you've never launched a marketing
campaign, you've never done packaging design, you've
never had to fire anybody, you've never raised
capital, you have never had to motivate a
group of people after you just lost your
shorts in the marketplace, et cetera, there's a whole
set of skills you may not realize
you need and you don't have them.
And also, as per tonight, you
may not realize you need them.
You may not realize you need them.
And so, as per tonight, you have to
think like a scientist and say, well, that hypothesis
didn't quite work.
So the previous sessions, the nuts and bolts,
have been talking about the skills that you
may not know you needed.
Tonight we're talking a little
bit about thinking like a scientist.
But I found that when I examined...
And, you know, this wasn't a...
I'm sorry.
This wasn't a rigorous analysis, but I spent
a lot of time talking to entrepreneurs that
I've worked with, some of whom have had
conspicuous successes, some of whom have had epic failures.
This is the two-bullet summary.
I'm going to make some closing remarks.
And we may actually end a couple minutes early.
But I'm going to open
it up to you guys now.
Are there questions that I should have asked
you or things that I should have talked to
you about?
This is the only session in Nuts and
Bolts where we actually dive into these sort of
human questions.
And then the wrap-up session will be a success
story that Marina has, send you out with a
buzz.
It's a great story.
You will enjoy it.
You will find it enlightening.
You're welcome.
But first, do you have any final
questions, comments, thoughts that you'd like to pursue?
Yes, sir.
Go ahead.
So assuming that you need three, four, nine
attempts to make something of value, how do
you...
What are some best practices to
give yourself that kind of runway?
Well, there's a couple of answers for that.
Many people who become entrepreneurs fear
that they are unemployable afterwards and
that if you go down this
road, you'll never get a normal job.
I have found that to be not true.
What I have found, in fact, is that
there are companies out there who want what they
call change agents.
That means you're not afraid
of a blank sheet of paper.
And that you might be a little
bit more likely to be a failure.
And that you might be able
to contribute some creative out-of-the-box thinking that
they are lacking.
And so one answer, one I have employed
a few times, is to weave in and out.
Go get a normal job
is the translation of all that.
And after about two years, I
end up thinking, God, I'm bored.
And to the dismay of my family, I
think, I just got to go start another company.
And another is...
What?
Well, of course, the happy answer is
your business succeeded and you got some runway
because you just put some money in the bank.
And you have some credibility.
But again, if you go to the right
places, I actually know a couple of investors who
straightforwardly say, Bob, I just don't want
to screw around with anybody who hasn't already
had a failure.
And there's two reasons.
One is they don't know they can fail.
Oops.
And the other is they've not shown me
that they have the right to do it.
They've not shown me that they
have the right to do it.
So I can't do it.
And I have to do it.
I have to do it.
And I've got to do it.
They have the resilience that's required to succeed.
So in an odd sort of way, if you go
to the right people and say, I made an effort here,
I did a lot of good
things, the end result was not successful.
Boy, did I learn a lot.
I want to bring what I
learned on somebody else's nickel to you.
It's not a bad pitch.
So the two ways are if you could
pick yourself up and go right back to it,
you won't be unappealing to everybody.
People will not regard you as having the
plague if you go to the right places.
And the other is, well,
sometimes you just think, all right,
I should weave back into the corporate
world and see what's going on there.
Maybe I can add something.
Maybe I can learn something.
Maybe I can make my family calm down
a little bit because I have a steady paycheck,
which is a novelty.
So good question.
Thank you.
And would you pass the mic?
What are your thoughts on waiting to start
a business, trying to do a day job,
get it to a point where
it looks like it might be feasible,
and then flip the switch, you know,
full time, or dive all the way in
and actually spend hundreds on your effort to do that?
I think that's a tough call probably,
and it's just based off
your experience with whatever you see.
That's a really good question.
Oh.
In the first session that we had, I
walked you guys through sort of a back
of an envelope analysis.
How much money do I need to make?
How much is a customer worth?
How many customers do I need?
Can I do that?
And I would argue against going all
in until you have done, you know,
a perfect job.
You know, you've got to be a good customer.
You've got to be a good customer.
And we've done at least
some of that kind of analysis.
I think people get swept away by their passions.
This is such exciting technology,
and it's moving so rapidly.
I have got to get in on this and
grab my spot at the front of the line.
But, you know, pioneers have arrows in their backs.
And so I would say if you
have assessed the market a little bit,
and you're thinking,
think realistically that you could make enough
money to have a sustainable business, then
back up if you have not done
those things it is not the right time.
If you have done those things
it might be the right time.
A lot of people are arguing these days and
I think there's wisdom here and doing it in
small steps is almost like a side hustle.
It's easier with the service
business than with the product business.
But go out there and make some
mistakes while you still have your steady paycheck.
Validate, validate, validate and then when you're
ready you can go forward to others
and say I've already done all this validation.
Now I'm going full time and I'm seeking investment.
Here's what I've learned.
Here's what I want to use the money for.
It's much more solid pitch.
Deploy passion wisely I guess.
Thank you for the question.
It's a good question.
Yes sir.
Thank you for answering that series of tools.
With the exception of your book, what other
books do you think are essential as entrepreneurs?
I serve a rule of thumb when I'm looking
at business books which is that I like the one
that's the shortest.
Because having been in the publishing.
Publishing business a little bit.
I know that most 200 page books
would make a great 50 page book.
But the publisher says Bob I can't
sell a 50 page book for $30.
Say the same thing four times over.
And then I can sell it.
Again I'm oversimplifying.
But.
You read a lot of business books.
Right.
So with that as preamble.
I like the Lean Startup.
Which I think is useful.
And though it's not specifically about entrepreneurship.
There's an absolutely awesome book simply titled Leaders.
And I'm sorry I cannot
remember the names of the authors.
But there's some.
There's two of them.
Warren Behn.
B-I-E-H-N maybe.
I'm not sure.
And I pull it out every couple of years.
Because they talk about what leadership is really all about.
And it's very short.
I think it's an awesome book.
It's brief.
And boy it really hits home on some important points.
When I wrote my book a couple years ago.
People were saying I should write a book about leadership.
And I said I don't know.
I don't know.
And people were starting to be
asked to go back to the office.
They were rebelling.
There were phrases popping up everywhere
like quiet, quitting, the great resignation, etc.
And the thrust of my book at the
time was how do you start a company?
At least as a starter kit.
So I touch on questions like how do you
interview to figure out are you looking at the right
person?
And if you've made a hiring mistake.
If you hire enough people you will make mistakes.
How do you determine that it's time?
It's time to fire them.
And how do you actually do that without laying
waste to the morale of everybody else in your
company?
So there's a lot of sort of practical stuff.
And almost as a lark I
started interviewing other entrepreneurs who almost immediately
started telling me about the failures they'd had
and what they learned from it and how
they felt about it and how they're now succeeding.
And I thought oh my goodness this is valuable substance.
I've got to rewrite the whole book.
Which I did.
And so it's got a somewhat
different thrust from some of the others.
But I like the Lean Startup.
I love this book Leaders.
It's more useful as a management guide
than as an entrepreneurship guide but valuable nevertheless.
So anyone else before I
pull the plug on tonight's talk?
Okay.
Thank you for your questions.
Oh.
Yeah.
Thank you.
And by the way if you haven't chosen
to stay in touch scan that QR code.
Okay wrapping it up.
Three things I want you to remember.
Entrepreneurship has many rewards for certain people.
But it's not for everyone.
If it's not for you in
many ways you should be glad.
It means you have a
chance of having a normal life.
Thank you.
And just by giving this information to other
people and sharing with them when you are
around that sort of portfolio of self Canyonچ
Some of this information by people that subscribe
or rely on me is important to me.
And it's amazing to me that the guide to success
can get to as many people in the world as
many as 30.
So if you want to promote your business
teachers or several other people around the world,
there are wszystkie info apps in the chat.
They can find you down below.
your resilience and one day you'll have your success.
So thank you very much.